so I want to talk about the I want to
talk about the Seleka suit mm-hmm budget
najiba nakiya eight and this was sort of
it's still in line with the whole
practice of non conflict that we've been
discussing the practice ready practice
of Nibbana the ultimate not conflict and
so it's called Sulekha and translated as
usually translated as defacement that
it's kind of a which means like a
wearing away of passions the wearing
away of evil hmm
young awesome yeah awesome to get those
away and it's translated in the party
dictionary as when austere penance mmm I
think it usually it's connected with
that view of self-mortification whereby
you purify yourself you purify the
unwholesome states of your mind by
enduring certain physical hardships so
by by going through certain ascetic
practices you get to erase the lust from
your mind and so on to do that was
that's the common view common practice
yes and so yeah so the the Jains for
example mmm one of the practices is
called sallekhana which is the fasting
to death starving starving yourself and
by gradually starving yourself you
gradually you slob lost aversion
delusion you know that's the idea behind
and you end up in the Barney Barney yeah
and so is it whole again that whole idea
I'll I'll practice this thing I'll do
this thing and it's going to result in
in purification of me yes sir
I will for example be nice to others and
it's gonna get rid of money over yeah
it's one the resulting in freedom from
a version so all the kindness and
compassionate acts are impressive
austere practices oh yeah what we're
entering not a degree of those is even
necessary yeah it's like the sense
restraint in virtual often goes hand in
hand with austere practices and it's
necessary in the basis but it's not that
which purifies you but that which
enables you to understand what real
purification is so this selector this is
from the Buddhist he's explaining it
what what's the latest from any point of
view and I won't read it word for word
just a few sections mm-hmm
so the monk maha chunda asks the buddha
when will serve various various views
arise in the world associated either
with self or in regard to the world now
does their banding and relinquishing of
those views come about in a bhikkhu who
is attending only to the beginning of
his methods meditation training so
anyway the Buddha replies as to those
various views about self and world if
the object in relation to which those
views arise which they underlie in which
they are exercised upon is seen as it
actually used with proper wisdom this is
not mine this I am NOT this is not my
self then abandoning and relinquishing
of those views comes about yeah so you
will abandon your views if you
understand what they depend on
not if you psychologize your way out of
them but if you meditate if you
concentrate your way out of them it's
wild those views are there see the
object of those views it's underlined by
the views which means that the
underlying cause of your views in regard
to this or that is they're
simultaneously present with this or that
otherwise it would not be engraved by
such-and-such view so you cannot
overcome that view simply by using that
view to kind of work your way out of
whatever you have a view about so the
practically speaking sensualities of
view for example sensuality is a view that
for example sensuality is a view that
whereby perversion is established of
that which is fundamentally naturally
inherently repulsive you deem as
attractive it's because of purview so
that view is in regard to attractions in
regard to the object of the senses
so you can now say no to all of the
objects of the senses for the rest of
your life that view will still remain
unaffected because you know that to undo
the view in regard to attractive and see
it as inherently non attractive you need
to understand what their view is you
can't just say no to the object of that
view which is sense object no can you
just say yes to the object of that view
which is your senses but if you
understand the necessary basis for the
object of your view that you want the
his desire to words you will abandon the
view and in this case the necessary
basis for anything attractive is non
attractive that's the necessary basis
repulsive is the necessary basis for any
form of sensual desire can you have
essential desire towards some somebody
else without body of you body of that
person being being a necessary basis for
any manifestation of their desire
impossible so if there is no sense
desire they can arise apart from the
body the bodies it's necessary presently
enduring simultaneously enduring basis
for their desire for the object of your
view that this is attractive so then if
you understand that your view that this
is attractive is fully within the non
attractive what you deem non attractive
or to them repulsive but not before or
after but as a container of anything
attractive and anything anything that
you have desired towards you will
abandon any desire toward attractive
because you could see it basically it's
within the nature of non attractive
which is repulsive dangerous and so on
but you will not erase that view you
will not face it simply by adhering to I
will always look only at the ugly for
the rest of my life I will not look at
the object of beauty of any kind sound
smell taste touch I will
only in your pain witness pain and look
at the pain in hope that I will erase my
basically view of desire towards what I
deem attractive and that's why you will
never erase that desire because it's not
rooted in the object of it yet now you
are either saying yes to or not but it's
routine understanding of that desires if
you want to erase the desire you have to
understand basically the presently
enduring necessary condition for your
view of attraction the present enduring
necessary condition for your view of
repulsion and hatred because if you do
that's how you abandon it without
actually having to deal with the objects
and that's what we have said even for
the target that he sees beautiful and
agreeable things in the world but what
the target that doesn't have is desired
and lost in regard to them because he
has abandoned the view that those things
are beautiful in that desirable sense
so the only effacement the only
starvation or greed aversion delusion
that can happen cannot occur through
method cannot to cook her through
observance cannot occur to any form of
mechanical practice mechanic meditation
technique it can only occur through
understanding greed aversion delusion
that's what it erases them once and for
all
the next section of that suit sir goes
into the the eighth attainments visits
so vaginas in the highest a in mind and
the Buddha says that one who is
practicing jhana or his other states he
might think I am abiding in that
Sulekha you know starvation of the
unwholesome the raising of I'm abiding
in that but is it is not these
attainments that jhana
that is called that you're raising yeah
that's a layer because jhana does not
necessarily mean understanding you might
have understood things to the extent
necessary for you to be draw yourself
from it understood that the extent of
sensuality understood the extent of any
concern of emotional involvement with
the world but jhana will not provide you
with the fundamental understanding of
that sense of self and ownership which
is the root of all it's root of
sensuality root of anger root of
everything and without that effort to
understand and without that
understanding of the Buddhist teaching
even John I cannot provide you with that
sure if somebody without any Buddhist
Buddhist help or instruction develop
jhana overcomes sensuality overcomes
everything he'll have much greater
chances of then practicing correct
Celica by developing the right view but
it's not the right view it's not the
automatic result of the John so that's
why we said the one who thinks I'm in
the John and that's why I'm approaching
all of it all greed all aversion all
delusion he's not correct because John
is will not have fruit all of it yeah
it's just that is called a pleasant
abiding yeah no boys
secluded from unwholesome state secret
secluded from what is secluded from any
hindrance it's very pleasant peaceful
abiding and I mean one on numerous
occasion the Buddha just said that's
dividing you everybody should strive for
but again in itself
it will not really result in that
fundamental starvation of religion
starvation of ignorance did that it
cannot occur again afterwards so what is
then Sulekha according to the Buddha
this is this is how it should be
practice but others will be cruel we
shall not be cruel here hmm Sulekha
should be practiced thus that's how it's
done so what is it then how do you starve
so what is it then how do you starve
what is the necessary basis for cruelty
can you have clothing on your will so
the necessary basis for the view of
cruelty is the ill will the object of
your cruelty the necessary basis for it
is ill-will unquestioned ignored unaware
of ill will you then entertain the view
towards the objects of cruelty the view
of cruelty the view of harm and so on so
how do you abandon it you abandon it by
removing the necessary basis for it
and where is then Dale will which is the
necessary base for cruelty where do you
find your will is it just mysteriously
floating somewhere in space and time in
your mind and then occasionally pops up
or is it perhaps always inseparable from
and manifests through your choices and
your actions can you have ill-will
without the intention of real world can
you commit a bodily actor will will if
you haven't chose to act out of ill will
towards your will for the purpose of
your will so it will is where your
action is action by body by speed by
mind so that's where you should start so
it's not not doing anything you're not
starting things randomly on account of a
random observance because some teacher
told you to you know like what they like
to do these determination practices and
so it's you know for these three months
I will not eat with a spoon or something
and you see no relation to anything you
just assumed a random observance that
now you will not hear to which your life
but see you completely miss place to
practice your determination your
observance is based on this literally
this observable I will not use the spoon
or I will not eat sugar or I will not do
this for no other reason that you can
see that pertains to you understanding
or like removing greed aversion delusion
just through out of faith out of blind
kind of adherence to a method or like a
very common observance would be I will
sit you know in meditation posture for
five hours every day interested you that
painting okay how does that relate to
you really understanding the necessary
basis for your greed to the necessary
basis for your lust the necessary basis
for your distraction well you have no
idea you're just literally adhering to
this observance with wishful thinking
that will somehow erase things that need
to be erased and that's no different
than self notification even if you don't
go to the point of our refuse to breathe
and start myself to death like joint
sometimes do it's equally ignorant as
giving in to sensuality so you cannot
arrive at the correct practice of
erasing ill-will the necessary basis for
cruelty by mechanically adhering to set
up prescribes motions and methods and
steps why because that's no believable
is you will is in your motivation
towards those motions and steps and acts
you do by body speech your mind and
that's something you cannot have a
prescribed template that will always
point out that's something you always
have to find yourself in and then see
whether it's rooted in your will or no
Neil will so if you want to erase
cruelty and anything unwholesome you
must not lose the sight of your
motivation behind your own action by
body by speech and by mind by thought
like why am I thinking about this is it
because this doubt is so unpleasant I
want to get rid of it so basically you
have resistance in a version towards the
discomfort of not knowing enough of
something so that's rooted in your will
so you're entertaining your real world
by trying to get rid of doubt in such
sense
or same black more obviously sensuality
central thoughts might present
themselves as a possibility but you need
to say yes to it as the Buddha said you
need to welcome it entertain it and
accept it that's when those things are a
problem and all those welcoming and then
accepting our choices you make towards
it and then repeat them and repeat them
and repeat them so yes it will last
delusion distraction whichever will
translate it needs to be raised but the
only way to erase it is to see where
it's rooted and it's always rooted in
motivation behind directions so if you
don't make the effort to look at what is
the current action what is the prospect
of this action I'm about to do what is
it rooted in am i doing this out of
desire or non desired out of your will a
version or non a version so those act
need to be raised the ones that you know
are rooted in greed aversion delusion
nothing else and this whole domain is
invisible to people if they never start
practicing that like mindfulness in that
proper sense wait what is the context of
my present situation why am I doing this
what is the purpose what is the what
feeling is this rooted in that it's
presently enduring while I want to do
this or what to do that because if only
you can see the objects of your views
then you would be judging your views
based on the objects not based on the
motivation behind in other words talking
like for you for for somebody talking is
always rooted in wanted to distract
himself from the unpleasant feeling of
boredom for example but they had unaware of the
for example but they had unaware of the
motivation behind the talking the
underlying calls for them wanting to
talk and use it as a distraction so all
this is distraction
talking talking means distraction so
then that's the judgment so when this is
somebody else talking up he's just
distracting himself as if no talking can
be rooted in anything else except
distraction because they don't ever see
anything else in themselves but the
reason they don't see it it's not
because it's not there
simply because they never made here for
to see they remain adhering to talking
and then consequently the practice
becomes about avoiding talking I'll be
silent for the rest of my life if you
want to take that practice to the
extreme which is why the Buddha said
it's an ignorant foolish thing to do and
actually made it a wrongdoing for monks
to practice the vow of silence because
literally means you think the problem
isn't talking you can see that there is
ill will yeah evil is that the line of
your rule is there well you don't feel
it further by body by speech or by mind
so you recognize you will where it is
yeah you recognize your is strange
you're not doing anything
yep physically and then you ask yourself
so what they do next but there is the
intention of your wills yeah so so how
so is it the way you regard that your
will that motivation yeah see like you
can you can restrain like say say I be
able toward you you've done something
upsetting that upsets me so I restrain
my body so I don't physically harm you
in a car that I restrain my speech so I
don't wobble you have use you an account
of it I restrain my thoughts so I don't
wish you harm and cruelty but see now I
still have the pressure to find what I
need to do to get rid of the ill-will as
I wait why
why do I assume that view that I must
get rid of the ill-will oh because it's
unpleasant not so in reality all I'm
doing is acting out of trying to avoid
discomfort now I limited the extent of
my act on account of the discomfort of
you upsetting me the first limitation is
I don't do anything by body to avoid you
I don't do anything by speech the world
you I don't do anything my mind to avoid
you but I am doing something internally
trying to figure it out so I don't
endure it anymore and that's why you
subjected to it but you still want to
get to you you want to overcome you want
to overcome yes that's the general
overall value it will is something to be
overcome but you will never overcome for
real with your will if you keep craving
against the discomfort of it sure but
now you understand that so you stop
trying to get rid of discomfort
available that's how you end up overcome
you start the ill-will by not providing
fuel for it but that's the vation can
only happen on the level of the feeling
of your discomfort towards ill-will off
ill will notice a level not on the level
of you know like reasoning and
psychologizing and so on that can help
you to find out what is it that you need
to start so what the only one thing you
need to starve is your resistance
towards uncomfortable feeling full stop
yeah doesn't matter on account of what
has that uncomfortable feeling arisen it
doesn't matter what matters is whenever
there is discomfort felt I will not
crave to get rid of it and then
indirectly you then remove anything that
can be felt uncomfortable it will upset
suffering anything sensuality the first
you stop at the roots you starve the
roots basically that's the only way you
can starve a thing you can't starve a
tree by trimming in branches because it
will keep growing you can manage the
tree right by cutting its branches
but you don't want to manage because you
keep the roots keep growing which means
the more and more and you can't keep up
we're trying to trim it all but if you
find a way of killing of the roots as
the widow said then it's like a palm
stump left cut off at its root dead it's
very thing others will be cruel but here
well I won't because that you cannot say
that here they will be cruelty but I
won't feed it you know why yes yeah it's
the same principle so cuz that's what I
mean like as I said you are not not
cruel by not harming anybody physically
you're simply not expressing your
cruelty to the extent of physical action
and that's a necessary step yes then
you're not expressing your quality to
the level on the level of verbal action
mental action but you still crew
why because you still resist the
uncomfort the discomfort of whatever
upset has been caused to you if you stop
resisting the discomfort there is no
basis for the view of cruelty view of
harm is just it's removed and as that
simultaneous principle we keep talking
about literally these roots are
simultaneously present with your view of
cruelty these roots are the necessary
basis for crude the necessary basis for
a body react mental act well act or
restraining from bodily act available at
mental act the necessary basis is
resisting the uncomfortable feeling of
of the situation which then manifest
through cruelty and harm now a
restrained manifestation of cruelty and
harm through my physical action verbal
action mental action but for as long as
I don't approve my resistance my craving
against the uncomfortable feeling of any
kind I am liable to cruelty but if I
approve that resistance I am incapable
of cruelty even if I don't think about
my physical
mental actions anymore it cannot
possibly be rooted in crude and that's
what again every action is intention not
every action is what you do by body
speech your mind what you do by body
speech your mind
the comma is so because of the intention
the determines that come and that's all
gonna set every action is intention so
if there is no intention of resisting
the discomfort craving for more comfort
on the level of your feeling craving for
indolence towards neither confident
discomfort if there are no such
intentions there are no manifestations
of view of sensuality view of cruelty
view will will view of anything
basically discrepant with your existence
and that's the true salaita you have
raised the necessary basis the necessary
framework for everything and all some
ever [Music]
[Music]
others will kill others will take ways
not given beam on unsellable speak fall
certainly shadows will not be verges
basically others we go against the
virtual and the level of their body and
let along the speech in mind so this is
balancer 44 examples hmm
but the last one says others will adhere
to their only views hmm hold on to them
and not to relinquish them and
relinquish them with difficulty that we
shall not adhere to anything yes you
will not hear you cannot help but have
views but you can't help whether you
choose to question it or choose to not
question it simplify not questioning
your own views you are adhering to them
you cannot say oh I will not hold 20
views because that is your view that you
hold you can recognize that you're bound
to hold some view and then question what
you hold and thus you will not be the
one that adheres to the views you will
not be the one that will have difficulty
relinquish interview when you see it as
unwholesome rooted in unwholesome rooted
in a contradiction we spoke the other
day about this but the current is
subject of entitlement hmm well I think
that's that connects basically to that
the root of the entitlement is a route
to that not questioning your position
assuming he taking at face value taking
for granted and an entitlement is the
product of it that manifests again
through directions by body by speech or
by mind you cannot be entitled if you
don't act in an entitled manner by body
by speech or by a thoughts
so to entitle me and you know the
fundamental entitlement
he's the entitlement to life health and
youth or intoxication with life health
and youth like everybody feels entitled
to be alive yeah but you're not entitled
to the next breath exactly why because
you just never questioned of entitlement
it's mine it's mine
how is it yours so are you new cooking
control of it this means you can prevent
it from disappearing you can't you can't
so then that means your entitlement is
just fully view view that you refuse to
let go of refuse to question refuse to
basically drill into it like entitlement
to health you are healthy but if that
changes you cannot do anything about it
so how can you be entitled to help when
it's not even in your own control level
or entitled for others to treat you oh
that's that's a whole new layer now
exactly that's when you add this
entitlement to the behavior of others
that you demand and you you feel
entitled to request a song and again
that's that's another thing that it's
sort of obviously explaining the sutras
whereby foreign around who is removed
any and every sense of entitlement even
if the highway robbers are stacking and
chop his limbs one by one
he he will not hate them because he
doesn't even feel entitled to him body
so then ripping up his body cannot
contradict that entitlement that he does
not have does he cannot hate them or
fight against them so others going back
a bit others will be cruel but I what
others shouldn't be cruel yes like me oh
yes yeah yeah it's not others will be
cool yeah what do you expect others are
bound to be cruel because no they will
be cruelty they will be greed they will
be diversion
the desire and you projecting that there
must not be cruelty anywhere in the
world it's basically wishful thinking product
it's basically wishful thinking product
of your own entitlement oh look I found
this great teaching of the Buddha the
Dhamma that's I'm entitled to demand
everybody to follow it and that's a
quite a naive notion ignorant notion or
on account of it I demand a certain set
of behavior by everybody because that is
the ultimate truth again your own
entitlement speaking listen so
you can't have the world you know go the
way you wanted to do no and the only
reason you would have even such a
inkling of such an expectation is cos
you know question your own views and
your own entitlement entitlements
so it's things like this done finding
where the problem really is yep
addressing that yeah they're not
expecting or trying to deal with it
externally not expecting others who they
are gonna respect you know do the same
thing as you do yeah so you must be okay
with okay find a way to be oh yeah you
haven't well that's part of your own
practice correctly you must be okay
I guess the Buddha said the wise one who
is practicing for enlightenment will be
enduring the abused and unpleasant words
of others in the same sense you endure
heat cold elements wind rain in
everything else that you have to endure
physically of not saying you cannot like
literally like even the most insane
person would not have an entitlement to
change the weather or to control the
weather you need to become extremely
rational but even then you realize it's
kind of future well the same attitude
recognize the futility of trying to
change it is others so instead of no
they should not speak cruelly
to me and abusively no I will not be
cruel and abuse when this is encountered
in my experience I will endure it on the
same level I and your heat called hunger
discomfort cuz it is on the level of the
elements others are elements for you
basically they behavior is neither your
problem nor your responsibility and you
making it your problem or your
responsibility is you acting out of your
own entitlement which is rooted in you
avoiding your own responsibility if I
see that in the danger of the monastic
tradition so yeah the phone that comes with it
so yeah the phone that comes with it
it's sort of the slit elevators
entitlement I mama it doesn't it doesn't
is that encouragement is actually rooted
in in something that even precedes the
form and the tradition monastic or
otherwise it's rooted in virtue the
extra virtue sila that is necessary for
uprooting entitlement order raising
greed aversion delusion is the first
pattern syllabus Bonamassa we spoke
about it before it's not like your rites
and rituals that we all know a
ridiculous and silly the word is actual
virtue and duty your sense of duty your
sense of virtue has to be a fat at first
so how do you abandon the FATA without
breaking a virtue without abandoning
your duty well your binary by seeing
where the view towards it is rooted at
so that whole tradition and form and
this is what we must do this is what
everybody must do and as a Buddhist to
do this it's all rooted in that same
kind of non-negotiable nature of virtue
so when you get monastic tradition more
than one previous ones the future ones
it is going to be extension of that same
thing but actually
if you start questioning not like not
questioning virtue by doing the opposite
of virtue but questioning the purpose of
virtue while you're virtuous that's
already how you start seeing what is the
necessary basis for maintenance of the
factor of this is my duty I must do this
and I must not do that that's I mean if
you reflect upon your virtue there has
been pretty developed beforehand if you
reflect on it correctly the point will
come when you get to understand that
it's not about what I'm doing which is
I'm keeping this virtue it's it's about
what I'm not doing any more what I will
not do so I don't care what I will do
all I care about is things that I will
refrain from doing and at that point you
refraining from doing ceases to be your
doing you just become something that
holds you and maintained so that whole
entitlement of all is a Buddhist
tradition this is what you must do this
which you must say this is your behavior
this is the extension of the factor of
syllable para mas
and sometimes people get the sense of it
the duty of virtue is imposed on you and
it is and people get a sense of it but
they don't know how to understand it so
instead they dismiss the virtue as a
whole and then they try to argue that
you don't need to keep the pace that you
in order to practice the dominant
because they don't see any other way
other than fetter when taken and no fact
that if I don't take it at all [Music]
well that's not what the Seleka is you
know the osteopath exactly so that's I
mean so if somebody thinks that you are
avid other country by being virtuous
that's another wrong way of thinking you
gonna experience that erasing or one
also because you agree the version
delusion is not rooted in in your acts
of sensuality not abstaining from
sensuality it's rooted in your view of
sensuality so you can abstain all you
want for the rest of the life if you
don't actually make the effort to
understand it you won't be free from it
sure abstaining from sexuality is always
better than non abstaining even if you
don't know that's a good I said even if
a monk doesn't get anywhere in his
practice doesn't develop any distinction
any knowledge if he spends the rest of
his monastic life crying in tears in
pain of restraint it's still better than
non restraint
even if none of his wrong view views
diminution account of it it's still
better but you you don't want to
practice just oh it's still better you
wanna practice to be free from view cuz
then restraint will cease to be
unpleasant then you'll be free from that
fetter of needing to like like restrain
yourself and so on needing to do it for
example that the practice of confessing
hmm what you've done yeah does not
purify you yeah he just basically
manages you from eroding even further
but he does not approve the roots yeah
because that's what it's in monastic
life I know I know people say that's why
you apologized you're gonna apologize
when you've done something wrong yeah
exactly and that's now your gratuitous
view apology is good if you've done
something wrong
it will next time it will basically
allow you to catch yourself before you
go that far cos it's unpleasant to sort
of admit you made a fool out of yourself
and so on but it can actually serve with
a good purpose but if you then over do
that in a sense of now you develop the
view that apology purifies --is you by
going through the motion of apology I
approved the basically unwholesome that
made me do such a such thing for which I
have to apologize
and that's no different than believing
if I enter this holy river my last
diversion delusion will be washed away
by this water that the Buddha mocked in
the suitors oh so then I should not
apologize no you should apologize but
don't entertain the views on account of
it
that's that apology should be used so
that you can to help you basically next
time don't need to apologize so it's
your way of what you do exactly the more
you are aware of what you're doing the
more you'll be then aware of why you are
doing it and that's where the roots are
that's where the problem is so it's not
like oh I shoulda should I not apologize
and now that you kind of kept that
erosion prevented it from going further
now ask yourself why did I end up in a
position for which I had to apologize
wherever my actions rooted where was my
motivation at and then though then you
actually you will also realize on some
occasion that actually even if others
are upset I have no need to apologize no
reason to apologize because you know
clearly surely confidently they was
rooted in non-greed non aversion and on
delusion and you know that because you
would not mind apologizing but you won't
recognize that well like that wrongdoing
even in things that are actually wrong
by body by speech your mind it's not
rooted in those things it's rooted in
greed aversion delusion underlying them
it's rooted basically in your motivation
for it like we spoke about it before
like powers Blount speech for most
people is full of ill-will full of
passion and that their own limited mind
has no other way of comprehending it
except the only way they can comprehend
it for themselves which is whenever I
raise my voice is because I'm angry thus
who ever ever raises the voice they must
be angry
and you will never find out whether
that's really the case or not because
you're unaware of your own motivation
they want me I can raise my voice out of
pure compassion out of pure concern
because this person won't hear it
otherwise
puttin it again with the example of
confession hmm the person might
compassion the good thing exposing the
fault but then you use that to hide the
fault yeah yeah I just hear it well you
feel like oh it's my duty to confess and
now that my duty under there no your
duties to approve that because of which
you ended up in a position that you have
to confess things that's where there was
that instance of that man who came to
hood and said oh I can't keep all these
rules it was hundred and something at a time I
it was hundred and something at a time I
can't keep all of this it's just too
much I want to leave the monastic life
and the Guru said can you keep the three
rules yes
okay that's easy okay well don't do
anything that you know it's rooted in
greed don't do anything that you know
it's rooted in a version don't do
anything that you know it's rooted in
distraction and that monk became an
ardent on account of the three rules the
three proper erasers so when people
cannot see things on that level where
they're rooted that's when they need
these rules to keep them in check but
keeping the rules will not necessarily
remove the roots if you just make them
proliferate further which is a necessary
step for everybody who starts but in
itself it's still rooted in your greed
aversion delusion in itself it's the
Lavetta
it's part of that suitor this isn't just
as there is an uneven part there is an
alternative even par for the unfor the
one who is truly is the alternative non
cruelty yep so person given to kul Tiras
non cruelty to which to avoid it
so there is cruelty I noticed that I see
that within myself so I have an option
there isn't that's what that's exactly
what means there is always an option
because cruelty is not rooted in set of
circumstances if cruelty was really
rooted in what you said to me there is
an option then to follow a certain set
of behavior towards what you said but
it's not the cruelty is rooted in my
choice to accept that is a reason for my
choice to not accept that is a reason in
other words qualities rooted in my
choice to be true or to be not to be
sensual or to be not sensual so any
could you serve it if you see the
motivation there is if you see the
motivation of cruelty you see your
responsibility for quality that means
you see your choice so you're able to
see the other phenomena the option of
non cruelty becomes apparent
so you can choose that exactly because
it's an option while that other options
remain while the option of cruelty
remains exactly so doesn't take away
here exactly so your option of non
cruelty is not rooted in removing the
option of cruelty
no it's rooted in not entertaining it as
the Buddha said no welcoming it nor
delighting in it not acting either by
not doing these things you are choosing
then the option of non cruelty but yours
you need to discern that on account of
your on account of discerning your
responsibility for crude your
responsibility for the world your
responsibility for sensuality sensuality
is not in the beautiful things in the
world a version it's not in ugly things
in the world it's in your choice
and every action is in tension
and the suits of things a little bit
more to this is over it ends in this
racism that one who is himself sinking
in the mud should pull out another who
is sinking in the mud such thing is
impossible the one who is that one who
is himself untamed undisciplined
defilements punished extinguished you
tame another fits what we spoke about
all this time so imagine you're
completely unaware of the spear of your
motivations that that's where the
problems are root that's what lasts is
rooted our version is rooted to be
completely unaware you have absolutely
no recognition within yourself towards
craving towards pleasure craving against
the pain craving to the destruction of
neutral you don't see any root you don't
see the existence of roots or where
those roots would exist and then you
teach somebody they will your teaching
would result in them singing those roots
seeing how to overcome them that is
impossible you cannot accidentally stumble upon
you cannot accidentally stumble upon
dhamma or for example like trying to
make people do the right thing
so you're cool ok well that's wrong who
might happen you might be right
in terms of teaching and non cruelty but
you do you are right for completely
wrong reasons you're not right because
you also see why non cruelty can result
in the protein the roots of cruelty you
don't see that so just whatever external
value you ended up circumstantial
adopting which doesn't like cruelty it's
good it's better than cruelty but in
itself it will not free you from the
roots of cruelty that's why they would
have said even the good karma is still
cannot you cannot free you from karma
all together because the roots of those
actions with the motivation of the
direction remains
non understood process when
you are not thief my stuff there's
unwholesome behaviors motivation is
complaining the others are yes another
little big it is it's it's too far
removed yet I should know he shouldn't
be like that he shouldn't speak like
this should you you might not help but have
should you you might not help but have
such thoughts but you can certainly help
yourself from expressing them and if
you're able to help yourself from
expressing them then you'll be happy
you'll be able to help yourself from
indulging them mentally if you're able
to help yourself not indulging mentally
you'll be able to understand its roots
that's what really compared to I was a
similarly for sensualities like it's
like a man in the water trying to like
find the two sticks in the water he's in
the water sticks and well he tries to
light the fire with them such things
impossible now the man the other as well
I can't light this fire crews to stay on
wet sticks away so he comes out in the
show he drives but the sticks are still
not quite dry he tries to light the fire
they want cuz they're still wet but if
he patiently keeps them maintains them
withdrawn from the water they will dry
out and then he can light the fire and
then the buddha said so it is for
summoners and brahmins who might live
withdrawn physically from sensuality
physically from unwholesome states as in
they stepped out of the water but
mentally they haven't withdrawn himself
from it as in the sticks are still wet
they will not light the fire of that
knowledge but those seminoma brahmins
who are withdrawn physically and then
mentally they recognize also their
involvement so they stopped fueling that
involvement then the sticks will dry out
and then they can light the fire
so of course you cannot have sticks dry
on the shore while you're in the water
but you can certainly not be in the
water and still have the sticks wet cuz
you know you haven't dried and properly
you haven't put them in the Sun you're
keeping them covered in the shade to
bury them in the soil we're trying to
sort someone else's well that's all the
result of this basic principle that's on
the level of your own mind there's a
another suture which is similar
since there are these ten ways of
subduing hatred to reach the hardest
thing with one thinking he has done me
harm but what should I expect mmm
what could you possibly expect from the
realm from samsara you're not in control
over your own breathing and heartbeat
and everything else what what level of
insanity is required irrational kind of
basis is required for you to expect
others to not do certain things it's
it's once you studies at all it's
actually it's actually inconceivable for
me to expect that the only reason it
wasn't inconceivable is because you kept
conceiving its to ignoring it to that
self basically inflated sense of
entitlement and it's just expecting
hopefully we'll exit the only reason
expectation is there because the basis
for such irrational expectation is there
the base is that it sort of he's not
seen correctly like you can't control
elements you can't control your own body
what a silly thing is to keep expecting
to control behavior of others or speech
of others and what a futile thing it is
because then you lose and why would that
matter what others do is say because
that's not where my suffering is rooted
to begin with the only reason it matters
is because you still blame that to be a
suffering and that all that blame is
already rooted in your own entitlement
which is caused by your own ignoring
your own responsibility in your own
choices
yes he's doing me harm - what should I
expect he's going to do what it's
similar I think it's in in territory got
to win right so he one doesn't get
worked up he was similar I think in
territory God we know that monk or a nun
said I know it was a monk who said that
to a grieving mother mother lost child
what she was grieving that she might
lose him mother come over the point was
if you stop and think about it you don't
know where that beam came from you don't
know where that being is heading what
possibility there is to grieve over
anything actually because grieving
implies a certain degree of control
where that came from and went away he
was taken from you that which was yours
how can you regard that which is yours
when you don't have a clue I came to be
and where it's heading literally
absolutely it's you cannot even think it
on a level of fantasy if you're honest
yourself you realize this is utterly
inconceivable inaccessible to me so
grief becomes impossible
how it came to be how a beam came to be
and where that being what happens to it
when it's not it's just after being
consumed you can choose a set of beliefs
this is what happened after somebody
dies this is what happens when you know
they dollar they solid it but all of
that is under that which means you
cannot possibly know or verify that
because that's all secondary to your own
you don't know where you came from and
where you're heading so grieving on that
external level of blaming people on that
external level becomes inconceivable and
it's pretty much there the state of
another gun you cannot possibly be
attracted or repelled by anything in the
books because he is unbearable
that that entitlement which is the
definition of existence any existence is
a degree of entitlement any bhava means
there is an extent of entitlement for
life for help for four years for
aggregates you remove that that becomes
even more inconceivable to extend that
entitlement in that further irrational
manner of you're entitled to demand
behavior of other sets of aggregates
that you cannot even fathom [Music]